American Association of University Women (AAUW), Syracuse Branch, Records
American Association of University Women (AAUW), Syracuse Branch, Records
1923-2011
American Association of University Women. Syracuse Branch.
11 linear ft.
Clippings, directories, files, minutes, photographs, publications, recordings, reports, scrapbooks and other material of the women's education and advocacy group.
2738239
Biographical History
The AAUW (formerly known as the American Association of University Women) was formed in 1881. The Syracuse Branch, which is heavily represented in this collection, was founded in 1889. There was also a Cazenovia Branch founded in 1969, for which there are several folders in the collection.
Members of the AAUW are women who have graduated from college with a Baccalaureate degree or higher. Today there are over 100,000 members in over 1,000 branches.
The mission of AAUW is to "advance equity for women and girls through advocacy, education, philanthropy, and research." To this end, branches meet regularly, plan and host events, work towards program, legislative and membership activities, and fundraise for AAUW scholarship awards. AAUW emphasizes advocacy for women and women's rights. The national organization has several periodical publications, Graduate Woman and Outlook, and occasionally publishes research material like How Schools Shortchange Girls as well as other material like The Change Management Toolkit to help members become more effective. Additionally, the branches regularly publish newsletters for local members.
More information is available on the AAUW's website at http://www.aauw.org/
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The American Association of University Women (AAUW), Syracuse Branch, Records consist of clippings, directories, files, minutes, photographs, publications, recordings, reports, scrapbooks, and other materials spanning from 1923 to 2007. The branch is still active.
Administrative material contains annual reports, bylaws, directories, membership information, job descriptions, financial records, and examples of the letterhead. It also includes material that is not specific to the organization, like guidelines for running meetings using parliamentary procedure and information on sexual harassment, diversity and education.
Audio-visual material contains two VHS and one audiocassette from between 1990 and 1992.
Cazenovia Branch files include material from the former branch of the AAUW founded in 1969 in Cazenovia, New York. There are branch bylaws, minutes from meetings, member directories, newsletters, and more. The material ranges in date from 1967 to 1980.
Material about the AAUW Conventions has been separated by National and State and include some programs and registration forms
Correspondence includes official correspondence like letters sent to all branches by the president of the national organization and also personal correspondence like thank you notes from local widowed members.
The Educational Foundation is a long lasting program to financially support women scholars. Branches of AAUW raise funds to support the fellowships and grants. The Educational Foundation also funded research about women in education, which resulted in many publications. There was a special program in the 1970s in which African educators visited AAUW branches to compare educational systems. The Syracuse Branch was chosen to host two African teachers in 1979 and the collection has memorabilia from that visit. The folders also include annual reports, financial information, lists of donors, directories and application information for the fellowships and grants, and research publications.
Memorabilia includes the numerous clippings and scrapbooks in the collection as well as awards and certificates earned by the Syracuse Branch. The newspaper clippings are most often from the local newspaper as announcements of AAUW activities or articles mentioning AAUW members. The scrapbooks include both photographs of events as well as newspaper clippings.
Minutes include general meeting minutes, executive board meeting minutes, and minutes from the special group, Armchair Travelers, but are inconsistent. For example, the years 1995 through 2000 are not represented in the branch minutes. In addition to branch meetings, there is also a folder of minutes from three 1989 meetings of the National Association of Social Workers.
Projects are both national and local in scale. The State Fair programs, the Scholarships list and the Talent Bank project were local, while the Women's Work/ Women's Worth and Legislation projects were national.
Publications includes newsletters and periodicals as well as single publications. Newsletters include the local Syracuse Clarion, the New York State newsletter, and a national newsletter, as well as a few miscellaneous newsletters. The periodicals are four titles from the national AAUW organization.
The Miscellaneous folder includes local information about other Syracuse organizations, notes about this collection, and some forms used by AAUW.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is alphabetical by subject. Folder contents are primarily in chronological order.
Related Material
Additional AAUW material may be found in the
Mary Gardiner Jones Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Politics, government and public administration; Activism and social reform; American Association of University Women.; American Association of University Women. Syracuse Branch.; Adult education of women -- United States.; Leadership in women -- United States.; Leadership skills for women.; Teenage girls -- Education.; Women -- Education.; Women in education.; Women -- Law and legislation -- United States.; Women -- Political activity -- United States.; Correspondence.; Compact discs.; Directories.; Awards.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Reports.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; VHS.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the AAUW, 1989-2007, 2011
Accruals
Additions expected at irregular intervals.
Inventory
- Administrative material
  - Annual Reports
    - Branch board, 1993-1997; summaries of board members' activities (Box 1)
    - Branch committees, 1961-1990; summaries of various committee and study group activities, including membership, education, legislation, hospitality, newsletter, more (Box 1)
    - National, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
      annual reports of other branches from the national AAUW, describing how different branches had responded to the questionnaire. Folder also includes annual report forms sent from the branch to the national organization.
  - Board member material, 1994-1995; handbooks, guidelines, roles and responsibilities (Box 1)
  - Bylaws
    - Branch
      - Bylaws, various versions, 1958-2009 (Box 1)
      - Policy notebook, 2001 (Box 1)
      - Revisions, 1975-1980 (Box 1)
      - Supplements, 1975-1988 (Box 1)
    - National, 1975-1997; charter and bylaws from 1975, 1977, 1979, 1985, 1987 and 1997; mission statement (Box 1)
  - Directories, 1931-2011; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Diversity material, circa 1970-2005; includes "Strategies for interrupting Prejudice" and a branch level checklist for organization leaders (Box 2)
  - Education, 1980-1995 (Box 3)
    "Education" by Corry Stork
    Equity for Women in the 1990s: Regents Policy and Action Plan with Supporting Background by the State Education Department of New York, 1993
    Gender Equity: A Report of the Select Seminar on Excellence in Education, by The Capital Area School Development Association, School of Education, The University of Albany, State University of New York,1995
    "Is Teacher Tenure Valid Any Longer?" by H. David Van Dyck
    NAESP Communicator (National Association of Elementary School Principals): July 1, 1980, July 15, 1980 and August 12, 1980
    "Promoting Self-esteem in Young Women: A Manual for Teachers" by the State Education Department Division of Civil Rights and Intercultural Relations, New York, 1989
    "Redefining the Goals of Education" by Barbara Kinne, NYSD Topic Chairman.
  - Financial
    - Bank statements, 2004-2010 (Box 2)
    - Dues, 2009-2010 (Box 2)
    - IRS forms, 2002-2010 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, receipts, treasurer's reports, budgets, more; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Handbooks, 1969-1970; 1977,; 1995 (Box 2)
  - Job descriptions, circa 1960-1985 (Box 2)
  - Letterhead, circa 1995 (Box 2)
  - Literature group, 1978-1983; reading lists (Box 2)
  - Members
    - Branch officers, circa 1960-1990; includes election forms for branch officers, list of names, and forms for switching officers (Box 3)
    - Division information, 1961-1987 (Box 3)
      1961-1963 and 1979-1980 Directories for New York State Division; 1980 letter about New York Division adopting the Virginia Division branch-to-branch; chart of branch membership 1978-1979; 1985-1986 committee members directory;1985-1986 Regional Directors; 1985-1986 NYSD Board; 1985-1986 State Division Presidents; 1986-1987 New York Division (2 copies); NYSD Branch Assignment with 6 Districts; 4 different maps of New York showing the divisional boundaries.
  - Membership booklets, 1958-1979; brief history of the organization, different kinds of membership, and the colleges that qualify for AAUW membership eligibility (Box 3)
  - Parliamentary procedure, circa 1960-1990; general articles, instructions and guidelines for successfully running meetings and following parliamentary procedure (Box 4)
  - Resolutions, circa 1960-1980; includes guidelines for resolutions (Box 4)
  - Sexual harassment information, circa 1980-2000 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1960-2000 (Box 4)
    "A plan for a branch evaluation and needs assessment;" "Recruit new AAUW members with Transitions Conferences;" "Resources for branch presidents in NYSD;" a guide to the living diagram for meetings; branch assessment worksheet.
- Audio-visual material
  - Radical Thoughts/ Outrageous Acts by Sharon Schuster, 1992; audiocassette (Box 4)
  - Shortchanging Girls, Shortchanging America by the American Association of University Women, 1991; VHS. (Box 4)
  - Voices of Choice by Mobilize for Women’s Lives, Feb 2, 1990; VHS. (Box 4)
  - Leadership Development: Member Leader Focus 2008 by AAUW, CD-ROMs; DVDs (Box 4)
- Cazenovia Branch
  - Charter and bylaws, circa 1967-1980 (Box 4)
  - Members, circa 1970-1977 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, circa 1967-1976 (Box 4)
  - Newsletter, circa 1968-1974 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1965-1975 (Box 4)
    includes 1960s AAUW guide called "Membership Hints" which suggests assigning "wedding-page clippers" to check newspaper wedding announcements for brides who have graduated from qualifying colleges
- Conventions
  - National, 1961-1985 (Box 4)
    1961 National Convention Program, Washington D.C.; 1961 list of speakers, panelists and resource leaders for the AAUW National Convention; 1985 Advance Registration and Certification Form for Branch Delegates and Alternates.
  - State / District, 1953-2005 (Box 4)
    1953 Program for Syracuse, New York Area Conference; 1962 Program for AAUW New York State Division Convention, "Our Diamond Jubilee;" "1977 Annual Convention" for New York State Division; 1978 Pamphlet "Living Exhibit" by Liberty-Monticello Branch for New York State Division Convention; 1987 Program for New York State Division Annual Convention, "Issues of Equity: Choices + Challenges = Action;" 2002 AAUW-New York State District III Fall Conference, "Living the Mission," registration form; memorabilia from 1989 New York State Conference held in Syracuse and 2005 York State District III Conference hosted by Syracuse branch
- Correspondence
  - General, 1929; 1972-1989; items from 1929 are photostats (Box 4)
  - General, 1929; 1972-1989 (Box 5)
- Educational Foundation
  - African Educators
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
      4 copies of information page; another information page; 2 copies of Background on African Educators Program; 1978 letter to Branch President; Questionnaire for Branch Evaluation 1978 African Educators Program; 1979 African Educators Program goals and objectives (3 copies); African Educator Host Form, 1978; 1979 letter to Branch President; 1979 African Educator Host Form; June 1979 letter that Syracuse was selected (2 copies); August 1979 letter; August 1979 Memorandum about visitors’ heath insurance; Biographical Sketches of both visitors; packet of information about adapting to a new culture; Newsletter focused on the visit; tentative daily schedule; Sept 1979 letter; tentative schedule note; Branch contacts for the two visitors; travel itinerary.
    - Information about Ghana and Kenya, circa 1978 (Box 5)
    - Memorabilia, 1978-1979; newspaper clippings and a packet from the Westcott Youth Organization (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1966-1967; 1978-1980,; 1998; from National AAUW Educational Foundation (Box 5)
  - Awards and grants
    - Directories, 1975-2000 (Box 5)
    - Guides, 1972-2001; guidebooks and application information (Box 5)
  - Brochures, 1969-1996 (Box 5)
    [1969] The AAUW Educational Foundation; [1973] The AAUW Educational Foundation; [1973] The Fellowship Program;[circa 1990] To give is to get;[1996] We’re changing the world, one woman at a time; [1996] Help change the world, one woman at a time.
  - Centennial Fund, 1972-1982; 2 brochures and an information newsletter about the Centennial Fund. (Box 5)
  - Finances, 1967-1985; See also Administrative Material: Finances. (Box 5)
    1967-1968 Branch Fellowships Report; 1975-1976 Report of Contributions AAUW Educational Foundation; 1975-1976 Ledger; 1975-1976 New York State Final Report; 1975-1976 Memorandum Committee Report: Educational Foundation: January; 1975-1976 hand written fund raising summary; 1976-1977 Syracuse Branch AAUW Educational Foundation typed fund raising summary; 1976-1977 hand written fund raising summary; description of the Century Club; 1977-1978 handwritten fund raising summary; 1977-1978 Report of Contributions; thank you note from national Educational Foundation; [circa 1978] thank you note from New York State Division; 1978 handwritten summary of fundraising effort, Canal Boat Trip, and correspondence about it; 1984-1985 EFP Chairman’s Report; 1985 Branch Named Unit endowment application and correspondence.
  - Hazel Clark Fund, 1972-2011 (Box 5)
    information from the estate, bank account statements, information update from 1978 with timeline
  - "Names Honored" programs, 1973-1999 (Box 5)
  - Publications, 1984-2001; 3 folders (Box 6)
    Beyond the Gender Wars: A conversation about girls, boys, and education
    Community Coalitions Manual: With lessons learned from the Girls Can! Project.
    Family advocacy and problem-solving through community partnerships: A manual
    Gaining a foothold: Women’s transitions through work and college
    How schools shortchange girls
    How schools shortchange girls: Action Guide
    How schools shortchange girls: Executive Summary
    Separated by sex: A critical look at single-sex education for girls.
    Si, se puede! Yes, we can: Latinas in school
    Voices of a generation: Teenage girls on sex, school, and self (2 copies).
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-2001 (Box 6)
    Information about the Educational Foundation; How Fellows are chosen; Organizational charts of funding; planning calendars; annual branch reports of activities; newsletter called "Fellows’ Network" from 1984.
- Memorabilia
  - Certificates, 1974-1999; includes awards for the Syracuse Branch Newsletter and for highest-per-capita donations towards the Educational Foundation (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1933-1990; includes local newspaper clippings as well as photocopied articles about women’s issues (Box 6)
  - Guest book from seminar, Oct 1970 (Box 6)
  - "History of AAUW, 1889-2004" (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1928-1935, part of display board (Oversize 5)
    - Publicity Scrapbook, 1947–1949 (Oversize 1)
    - 1943-1954 (Oversize 1)
    - 1937-1942 (Oversize 1)
    - 1967-1972, Cazenovia branch (Oversize 2)
    - 1934-1935 (Oversize 2)
    - 1937-1942, envelope of loose clippings (Oversize 2)
    - 1945-1947 (Oversize 2)
    - 1953-1962 (Oversize 6)
    - 1962-1963 (Oversize 3)
    - 1952-1958, includes loose clippings (Oversize 3)
    - 1954-1985, includes loose clippings (Oversize 4)
    - 1969-1970 (Oversize 4)
    - 1973-1975 (Oversize 4)
    - 1981-1993 (Oversize 6)
    - 1993-2003 (Oversize 6)
    - 2001-2002 (Oversize 6)
    - 2003-2011 (Oversize 6)
- Minutes
  - Board and general meetings, 1923-1943; 1961-1975; 6 volumes (Box 7)
  - Board meetings, 1975-1982; 1984-2001,; 2005-2011; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - General meetings, 1975-1982; 1985-2001,; 2005-2011; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Other, 1978-1979; Amrchair Travelers; 1 volume (Box 8)
- Projects
  - Arthritis Foundation, 1984-1987; two brochures and one annual report (1984), and correspondence circa 1987 (Box 9)
  - Awards given by AAUW, 1984-1987 (Box 9)
  - Childcare, circa 1988 (Box 9)
    Two projects, one named "Cooperative Action Planning- Dependent Care" and another named "Child Care Concern Project," both addressed child care. Folder includes photocopied information and articles about caregivers and sex equity.
  - Donations to AAUW entities and other deserving agencies, 2007-2011 (Box 9)
  - Legislation, 1972-1978 (Box 9)
    1972 AAUW legislative history and policy notes booklet;1973-1975 AAUW Legislative Program and Resolutions pamphlet;1975-1977 AAUW Legislative Program and Resolutions pamphlet;"Spirit of ’76 ERA" flier;1977-1979 AAUW Legislative Program and Resolutions pamphlet;1978 "The Equal Rights Amendment and the Family" brochure; 1978 mass distributed letter, "New Yorkers for Returnables;" [undated] AAUW’s Legislative Program brochure; [undated] For full and permanent equality… The Equal Rights Amendment."
  - Peace Curriculum, circa 1986; project for the New York State Division Task Force on Peace and National Security (Box 9)
  - Project WIDE, circa 1977; WIDE stands for Workshops In Developing Effectiveness. (Box 9)
  - Scholarship accounts and records, 2008-2011; bank statements etc. relating to local scholarships (Box 9)
  - Scholarships, 1954-1988 (Box 9)
    In 1955, the Syracuse AAUW organized a list of scholarship and grant opportunities for Onondaga County, New York, high school graduates. The folder also includes correspondence from 1988 about the scholarship project, Central Tech Scholarship winners, and other local scholarship recipients
  - State Fair
    - Clippings, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
    - General, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
      Programs and correspondence relating to the 1954, 1955 and 1956 New York State Fairs, in which the AAUW Syracuse Branch hosted a Film Festival in the Women’s Building. Also includes one Community Service Award ribbon.
    - Photographs, 1954-1956 (Box 9)
  - Talent Bank, 1972 (Box 9)
    1972 project in which Syracuse AAUW members submitted brief resumes on index cards (included in folder) to "governmental officials to make them aware of our desire to aid them in their selection of women for public service."
  - Women of Achievement award, 1984-1993; information about honorees including clippings, programs, etc. (Box 9)
  - Women’s Work, Women’s Worth, circa 1987; pay equity project; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-2009 (Box 9)
    instructions for building an AAUW banner, a program for "Women: the Equal Half of Humanity" from 1961, 1939 catalogue from the Annual Hobby Show of Central New York’s Branch, more
- Publications
  - Histories of the New York State division, various, 1954; 1970,; 1990 (Box 9)
  - Change Management Tool Kit, 2001 (Box 9)
  - Newsletters
    - Focus, 2002-2005 (Box 9)
    - New York Leader: Your Guide to Dynamic Branch Leadership, 1983-1989 (Box 10)
    - The Syracuse Clarion (formerly the Syracuse Branch Newsletter), 1954-1989; 5 folders (Box 10)
    - The Syracuse Clarion (formerly the Syracuse Branch Newsletter), 1990-2011; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous newsletters, other chapters, related organizations, etc. (Box 11)
  - Periodicals
    - AAUW New Yorker, 1985-1989 (Box 11)
    - AAUW Outlook, 1989; 3 issues (Box 11)
    - Graduate Woman, 1983-1986 (Box 11)
    - Graduate Woman, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Leader in Action, 1982-1989 (Box 12)
  - Program Guide, 1979-1981 (Box 12)
  - Techniques for Organizational Effectivenss, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Tool Catalog: Techniques and strategies for successful programs, 1971 (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-2006 (Box 12)
    January 1972 Membership list for the American Business Women’s Association, Syracuse Charter Chapter; [circa 1975] order form for AAUW Membership Film and Slide Shows; [circa 1976] secretary’s notes[circa 1978] Request form for New York State Division Travel Visitor; [circa 1980] flier called "Families Facing Change" (2 copies); 1980 invitation to celebrate four Syracuse Branch AAUW members 50-year-anniversaries;[circa 1992] pamphlet called "Federation Facts and Figures" and organization information and bylaws for Syracuse Federation of Women’s Clubs; 2003 brochure for the Syracuse Branch AAUW;2006 SCRC note that three scrapbooks were removed from the collection; [undated] Historian notes; [undated] timeline of AAUW history.